IU Oral History Archive 1991-1998
Indiana University Libraries
- Popoff, FrankApril 20, 1994, 91-249; 11 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 37 mminutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  foundation work; student attitudes; teaching vs. research debate
- Pratter, HarryMay 23, 1994, 91-262; 29 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 105 minutes;index; Freedman, Jean
  Born August 17, 1917 in Kiev, Ukraine, Harry Pratter was a professor of law at Indiana University Bloomington. In this interview he discusses his childhood, education, and arrival at Indiana University. He recounts student protests and riots on campus in the late 60s and early 70s, and discusses the impact of McCarthyism on the university. Further, he discusses the controversy over the Kinsey Institute.
  faculty council; Kinsey Institute; Maurer School of Law; University of Buffalo; University of Chicago
  Buffalo, New York; Chicago, Illinois; Kiev, Ukraine
  administrative assistant; law professor
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Howe, Irving; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B.
  African American students; campus change; Jews; Kinsey research; McCarthyism; student protests; student riots; student unrest; world War II; World War II veterans
- Prosser, FranklinApril 15, 1996April 17, 1996, 96-007; 51 pp.; 4 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 200 minutes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Born July 4, 1935 in Atlanta, GA, Franklin Prosser arrived in Bloomington as a post-doctoral student in the Chemistry Department under Professor Harrison Shull. Prosser was involved in the development of the IU Computing Center and the Department of Computer Science where he served as Director of Education. In this interview he discusses the development of the curriculum for the Department of Computer Science and the struggles to have the program recognized and accepted by other departments. Also, he discusses the process of tenure in the Department of Computer Science and shares his thoughts on the ethics of emerging technologies.
  Computing Center; Department of Computer Science; Hewlett-Packard; National Science Foundation; Texas Instruments; University Computing Services; Xerox Corporation
  Atlanta, Georgia
  chair; Director of Education
  Hagstrom, Stanley; Martin, Wayne; Purdom, Paul; Ryan, John; Shull, Harrison; Springer, George; Whitney, Dedaimia; Winkel, David; Wise, David; Wrubel, Marshall; Young, Steve
  chemistry; computers; computer science; computer science development; computer science program; computing; computing center; crescent renovation project; tenure
- Purdom, Paul W. May 16, 1996, 96-011; 39 pages; 2 tapes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Born on April 5, 1940, Paul W. Purdom came to Indiana University in 1971 as a professor and member of the faculty of the Department of Computer Science. A graduate of California Institute of Technology, he discusses the development of the field of computer science and the creation and development of the Department of Computer Science at Indiana University. Purdom speaks of departmental enrollment trends, funding issues, and the fight for the establishment of a Ph.D. program in computer science at Indiana University. In addition, Purdom mentions recent departmental issues including tenure and tensions.
  California Institute of Technology; Indiana University Department of Computer Science
  computer science development; departmental enrollment; departmental funding
- Rand, Leon December 17, 1993, 91-230; 14 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 31 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Leon Rand, born in 1930, served as chancellor of Indiana University Southeast beginning in 1986. He speaks of other experiences in his career, including his years at the University of Detroit. Rand discusses the history of Indiana University Southeast, its campus, and its service to a student population consisting of a majority of nontraditional students. In addition, he speaks of problems associated with decreased funding, the opportunities and advantages of distance education, and the Indiana University regional campuses in general. Finally, he speaks of the Indiana Commission on Higher Education and its role and impact in the state of Indiana.
  Indiana Commission on Higher Education; Indiana University Southeast; University of Detroit
  distance education; Indiana University regional campuses; Indiana University Southeast campus; nontraditional students; university funding
- Rawald, Ronald July 6, 1994, 91-277; 14 pages; 1 tape, 48 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Restricted: no commercial use by anyone not affiliated with Indiana University
  Ronald Rawald, a 1986 Indiana University alumnus, speaks of his years as a student at the university. A former student body president, he became intensely involved in student government and campus politics. He worked actively in the Indiana University Student Association, and through this involvement, testified in the Indiana General Assembly. As student body president, Rawald felt he made a significant impact on the issue of the high university cost for student health care with a compromise resolution he proposed, which was adopted. Rawald cites Harvey C. Bunke and a class Bunke taught as major life influences.
  Indiana General Assembly; Indiana University Student Association
  Bunke, Harvey C.
  student government; student health care; student presidency
- Reichmann, Eberhard February 3, 1997, 96-034; Not transcribed; 2 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour, 40 minutes; no index; Kraemer, Peter
  Eberhard Reichmann discusses his career as a professor of German in the Indiana University Department of German. He speaks of his experiences and the requirements of teaching, and of teacher training.
  Indiana University Department of German
  German professor
  teacher training; teaching
- Remak, Henry H. H. July 19, 1996; July 21, 1996; July 25, 1996, 96-020; 77 pages; 7 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 380 minutes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Henry H. H. Remak, born on July 27, 1916, discusses his family background and youth in Germany, his education, his long association with Indiana University and recalls much of the university's history from the years spanning 1936 through 1996. A long-time faculty member, Remak discusses his career in languages, particularly German and French, and speaks of the German Department and the Institute for Advanced Study. Dr. Remak comments on the beauty of the Indiana University campus, the social anti-Semitism he experienced in the United States, the effects of World War II on enrollment in the German Department, and German Americans and culture in America. In addition, he speaks of teaching, especially in the context of the Cold War, McCarthyism, and the Vietnam War and the unrest of the nineteen sixties. Professor Remak shares anecdotes about two of the most well-known figures in the history of Indiana University, Herman B Wells and Alfred Kinsey, and he speaks of the increased and misplaced emphasis on academic specialization, the teaching vs. research debate, and faculty tenure.
  Indiana University Department of German; Indiana University Institute for Advanced Study; Sigma Alpha Nu
  Bryan, William Lowe; Evans, Maurice Blakemoore; Frenz, Horst; Gallaway, Jesse James; Hitler, Adolf; Ittner, Robert; Kinsey, Alfred C.; Osthus, Carl; Payne, Fernandus; Stout, Selatie Edgar; Voss, Bert John; Wells, Herman B; Zucker, Edward
  Bloomington, Indiana; Germany
  1944 GI Bill; academic specialization; adult students; anti-Semitism; Cold War; communism; comparative literature; diversity; education; faculty tenure; female faculty; fraternities; German-Americans; German culture; German language; German literature; Great Depression; McCarthyism; Nazism; student protests; teaching; teaching vs. research debate; World War II
- Rich, Claude T. May 21, 1991, 91-061; 22 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 95 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Born on March 4, 1907, Claude Rich is a 1929 Indiana University alumnus who went on to establish a career of service to the university that spanned sixty-five years. Throughout these years, he held many different administrative positions including assistant alumni secretary, acting director of the student union, alumni secretary, which position became known as the director of alumni relations, director of the sesquicentennial celebration, and director of university relations. Rich comments on each of these jobs, his days as a student at Indiana University, and some of his colleagues including Herman B Wells and George "Dixie" Heighway. In addition, he speaks of his association with Hoagy Carmichael, the Board of Aeons, and Blue Key. He discusses the impact of World War II and the Vietnam War on Indiana University. Finally, Rich speaks of the university's participation in the development of international higher education systems and/or institutions.
  Blue Key; Board of Aeons; Claude Rich Scholarship
  Bryan, William Lowe; Carmichael, Hoagy; Heighway, George "Dixie"; Wells, Agnes E.; Wells, Herman B
  international higher education; Vietnam War; World War II
- Richardson, Dow L. April 18, 1994, 91-248; 11 pages; 1 tape, 23 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Dow L. Richardson, a 1928 alumnus of Indiana University, recalls his years as a student at the university. He speaks of the history of Indiana University and the changes it has undergone, especially those pertaining to the expansion and development of the campus. Richardson tells of his memories of his undergraduate years, including an episode of the infamous panty raids. In addition, he speaks of his involvement with the Indiana Daily Student, which led him to a lifetime career in the newspaper business. Richardson later became active in the Indiana University alumni association. He also describes memories of Herman B Wells and Hoagy Carmichael and comments on his impressions of Indiana University president, Myles Brand.
  Indiana Daily Student; Indiana University Alumni Association
  Brand, Myles; Carmichael, Hoagy; Wells, Herman B
  campus development; college traditions
- Richardson, John "Jeff" July 21, 1992, 91-129; 24 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 89 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on November 30, 1950, John "Jeff" Richardson earned his undergraduate degree from Indiana University in 1973, went on to Indiana University School of Law immediately afterwards, received his law degree, and earned his Master's degree from the School of Public and Environmental Affairs. A former student body president who served from 1972 to 1973, Richardson was extensively involved in campus politics, student government, and local politics and government in Bloomington. Some of the issues he discusses from his years as a student are the 1969 tuition increase, the Vietnam War, student protests and demonstrations, the Kent State University shootings, and women's rights. After completing three degrees, Richardson served as a member of the city council of Bloomington and later began working in Indiana state government. He recalls anecdotes involving Herman B Wells, Keith Parker, John Lombardi, and John Ryan.
  Ku Klux Klan; Monroe County Youth Shelter
  Grossman
  Lombardi, John; Nixon, Richard Milhous; Parker, Keith; Robinson, Eileen; Ryan, John W.; Sippers, Mary; Wells, Herman B
  1969 tuition increase; 1970 Kent State University Riot; campus politics; student protests; Vietnam War; women's rights
- Risk, Fred July 27, 1992, 91-132; 15 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 36 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1928, Fred Risk is a 1949 Indiana University alumnus who went on to earn his law degree in 1951 from the Indiana University School of Law. He discusses his memories of the university including the impact of World War II, the Korean War, and the growth of the university. He speaks of his involvement with the Acacia fraternity, and the difficulties of law school at Indiana University. Later, Risk became actively involved in alumni affairs and the Indiana University Foundation. He discusses the problem of funding for the university and for the individual student.
  Acacia; Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University School of Law
  Indiana University alumni affairs; Korean War; student funding; university funding; university growth; World War II
- Robertson, Edward June 13, 1996, 96-017; 27 pages; 2 tapes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Born on July 16, 1944, Edward Robertson, a member of the Indiana University faculty since 1978, became chair of the Department of Computer Science in 1982. He discusses the development of the field of computer science and the university's Department of Computer Science. Robertson also speaks of the various computer equipment used over the years, the decrepit state of Lindley Hall and its usefulness, departmental enrollment, the small number of female faculty members, and funding and its uses over the years. In addition, he recalls the time he spent at the University of Ghana attempting to create a department of computer science in an environment with severe limitations.
  Indiana University Department of Computer Science; Lindley Hall; University of Ghana
  computer equipment; departmental enrollment; female faculty; university funding
- Schilt, Alexander May 24, 1994, 91-261; 10 pages; 1 tape, 23 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Born on March 4, 1941, Alexander Schilt came to Indiana in 1970 to serve as the dean of student services at Indiana University Southeast, at which time he also taught one graduate class per semester. In 1976, Indiana University president John Ryan appointed Schilt to the position of chancellor of Indiana University East, a post at which he remained until 1980. In this interview, he discusses the changes that each of these campuses have undergone, and the positive aspects of each. In addition, Schilt speaks of the regional campus system at Indiana University, its possible future, and his philosophies on education, specifically in relation to Indiana University and its Indiana University regional campuses.
  Indiana University East; Indiana University Southeast
  Crooks, Ed; Ryan, John W.
  Indiana University regional campuses; Indiana University Southeast campus; Indiana University Southeast history
- Schmalz, Richard H. May 6, 1992, 91-101; 11 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 37 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on February 2, 1918, Richard H. Schmalz is a 1940 Indiana University alumnus who served for four years in the United States military after receiving his undergraduate degree. The son of a local businessman, Schmalz returned and began working in retail business, eventually coming back to the family business. He describes his years as a student at the university, including the impact of the Great Depression and Indiana University growth. He later became involved with the Indiana University athletic committee and is a former president of the alumni association. Schmalz also John Ryan's actions as a president of Indiana University.
  athletic committee; Indiana University Alumni Association
  Great Depression; local business; university growth
- Schurz, Scott October 30, 1991, 91-081; 18 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 72 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1936, Scott Schurz discusses how and when he became acquainted and involved with Indiana University. A reporter by profession, he became very active in the Indiana University varsity club and Friends of Music. In this interview, Schurz sings the praises of Indiana University, singling out the excellence of many athletic and academic programs including basketball, swimming, the School of Music, the School of Journalism, and many others. In addition, he discusses his association with Herman B Wells, Bob Knight, Jerry Yeagley, and Nelson Pointer, to name a few of the people discussed in this interview.
  Bob Knight Endowment; Friends of Music; Indiana University School of Journalism; Indiana University School of Music
  journalist
  Hesberg, Ted; Knight, Bob; Pointer, Nelson; Wells, Herman B; Yeagley, Jerry
  varsity club
- Searles, Richard C. March 17, 1994, 91-243; 20 pages; 2 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 69 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Richard C. "Rich" Searles was born in Massena, New York, in 1948. As a child, he lived in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, and Evansville, Indiana, then started as an Indiana University student in 1966. He talks about his experiences as a student in the late nineteen sixties, including his membership in the Sigma Nu fraternity and the Indiana University Student Foundation, and he puts his experiences in the context of the climate of the Vietnam War and racial tension. He describes his post-graduate career in the corporate world, as an employer, and as a member of the board of the Indiana University Foundation. He describes allegations of the mishandling of the Indiana University. Foundation's affairs. Searles offers his opinions on the administration of Indiana University from his student days to the mid-nineteen nineties.
  City Securities Corporation; Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University Student Foundation; Merrill Lynch and Company, Incorporated; Sigma Nu
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Peterson, John; Richardson, Ray; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  Little 500; fundraising; race relations; student life; student unrest; Vietnam War
- Seltz, HerbertMay 1, 1997, 96-038; not transcribed; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 103 minutes; Kraemer, Peter
  radio; teaching; telecommunications
- Shirley, Janet C. October 2, 1991, 91-079; 24 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 81 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Janet C. Shirley, born on October 4, 1934, is a 1956 alumnus who returned to work at Indiana University in 1979 in the Indiana University Foundation. She later worked for the alumni association and became director of alumni relations at Indiana University-Purdue University at Indianapolis, or IUPUI. In this interview, she recalls her years as a student, including her experiences as a cheerleader and those involving diversity on campus. Shirley goes on to discuss her later involvement in the Campaign for Indiana and the Herman B Wells Scholars Program. She also speaks of her experiences with Herman B Wells, Bob Burton, and John Ryan.
  Indiana University Alumni Association; Indiana University Foundation; student foundation
  Burton, Bob; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  Campaign for Indiana; cheerleading; diversity; Herman B Wells Scholars Program
- Shively, Leslie C.March 27, 1992, 91-090; 20 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 59 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Leslie Shively attended Indiana University Bloomington from 1972-1976 and attended the McKinney School of Law in Indianpolis from 1977 to 1980. Serving as the first student trustee on Indiana University Board of Trustees, Shively discusses his experience with other trustees and the decisions made during his time on the board. He also discusses the attitude and cliamte on campus in the 1970s. Finally, he offers his opinion on the future of Indiana University.
  Board of Trustees; McKinney School of Law; School of Business
  Evansville, Indiana; Indianapolis, Indiana
  student; student trustee; lawyer
  Harvey, Bill; Sperber, Murray
  student attitudes; student riots; Vietnam War; Vietnam War Protests
- Simic, Curtis R. October 20, 1993, 91-211; 29 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 77 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on October 10, 1941, Curtis Simic is a 1964 alumnus who worked at Indiana University for a few years in the area of fundraising. After nearly twenty years of working with several prestigious universities, including Yale and Berkeley, in the area of fundraising, Simic returned to Indiana University as the president of the Indiana University Foundation. He recalls his years as a student at the university and emphasizes the impact of the Cuban Missile Crisis and the assassination of president John F. Kennedy. Simic also discusses the Little 500, financial problems, university growth, and the changes the campus has undergone. In addition, he speaks of his relationship with Sam Yellin, Herman B Wells, and others.
  board of trustees; Indiana University Foundation; student foundation; University of California, Berkeley; Yale University
  Daugherty, Jack; Ehrlich, Ellen; Ehrlich, Thomas; Errenpreis, Irvin; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wallace, George C.; Wells, Herman B; Yelling, Sam
  Little 500; campus changes; Cuban Missile Crisis; diversity; fundraising; John F. Kennedy assassination; student activism; university funding; university growth
- Smith, Raymond April 5, 1996, 96-006; 18 pages; 1 cassette; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Raymond Smith, born in 1917, earned his graduate degree in 1939 from the Indiana University Department of Speech as part of the first class to receive a graduate degree from this department. Smith speaks of the Great Depression and the employment and financial constraints it inflicted. He served in the United States Army Air Corps during World War II as a radio instructor, after which he completed his doctorate at the University of Wisconsin in 1950. From 1950 through his retirement in 1982, Smith served as a professor in Indiana University's Department of Speech, later Department of Speech Communications. Smith discusses some influential members of Indiana University's Department of Speech and university faculty including Robert E. Barton Allen, Robert Milisen, Lee Norvell, and psychology professor, Snoddy.
  Army Airways Communication System; Indiana University Department of Speech Communication
  speech professor
  Allen, Robert E. Barton; Millisen, Robert; Norvelle, Lee; Snoddy, George Samuel
  Great Depression; radio instruction; World War II
- Smith, Stephen Kendall July 9, 1992, 91-121; 38 pages; 2 cassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour, 51 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Stephen Kendall Smith was born in Burlington, Vermont, in 1941. He moved with his family to Lafayette, Indiana, in 1952. He attended Indiana University from 1960 to 1964, lived in the Phi Kappa Psi fraternity, was actively involved in campus politics, and was student body president in 1963-64. He describes many aspects of campus life: fraternity life and "hell week," campus campaigns and elections, social events, the presidencies of Herman B Wells and Elvis Stahr, and campus reactions to the Vietnam War, the Cuban Missile Crisis, the Civil Rights Movement, and the assassination of John F. Kennedy. Smith describes his experiences as a Rhodes Scholar and briefly describes his post-graduate career.
  Army ROTC; Barnes and Thornburg; Barnes, Hickam, Pantzer and Boyd; Big House Coalition; Independent Party; Indiana Daily Student; Indiana University All-Campus Party; Indiana University Board of Aeons; Organized Party; Oxford University; Phi Kappa Psi
  Atkins, Tom; Bingham, Barry; Blase, David; Christenson, Carroll; Donovan, Mike; Edmundson, Frank; Hanson, Norwood Russell; Huston, Tom; Kemp, Gretchen; Kennedy, John Fitzgerald; Link, Goethe; Oswald, Lee Harvey; Owen, Kent; Polk, Jim; Scriven, Michael; Shaffer, Robert; Stahr, Elvis J.; Tesich, Steve; Wells, Herman B
  Breaking Away; campus politics; Cuban Missile Crisis; elephants; female students; fraternity initiation; fraternity life; fraternity pledgeship; John F. Kennedy assassination; Rhodes Scholarship; Vietnam War
- Snyder, John W.May 26, 1994, 91-264; 13 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 33 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  John W. Snyder was a professor of history at Indiana University starting in 1954. In his time at the university he also served as Associate Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences until 1969 when he left the university to become President at Westmont College. In this interview he discusses his research on learning problems and the SAT, student unrest in the 1960s, and changes to Indiana University during his tenure. Also, he comments the financial problems facing universities across the country and provides several amusing anecdotes.
  Indiana University Foundation; Westmont College
  Colorado; Santa Barbara, California